A Guide to the Papers of Bliss Carman, 1891-1929
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Bliss Carman in the Clifton Walter Barrett Library 1891-1929
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
7307-m
The collection consists of ca. 40 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The papers were a gift to the library by Gale Valentine Emery, in memory of her grandmother, Agnes Cook Gale, February 3, 2006.
Scope and Content
The collection consists chiefly of typescripts of poems copied out for Agnes Cook and letters to her.
Carman discusses the writing and publication of his poems; expounds the doctrines of Unitarianism and the fallacies of Christian Science; and shares misgivings (early in 1917) about Woodrow Wilson with his "moral cowardice and callous egotism." He also mentions the selling of letters from departed celebrities to autograph hunters and recommends she read Vachel Lindsay.
Correspondence mentions Richard Hovey, Mary Perry King, Odell Shepard, Anne Higginson Spicer, and Susan Hays Ward.
The collection also contains an inscribed photograph post card of Carman; three printed copies of his poems; a partial bibliography; and obituaries.
Contents List
- Series I: Manuscripts
  - 1893 May 10 "Afoot,", TMs, 3 pp. (Box-folder 2:1)
  - 1893 January 24"Berris Yare A Legend of the Briar Rose,", AMsS, 8 pp. (Box-folder 2:2)
  - 1893 February 20"Hilary Varen,", TMsS, 3 pp. (Box-folder 2:3)
  - 1893 March 19"In the Studio,", TMs, 1 p. (Box-folder 2:4)
  - 1892 November 30"In the Wayland Willows,", TMs, 1 p. (Box-folder 2:5)
  - 1892 May 2"In the Wings,", TMs, 1 p. (Box-folder 2:6)
  - 1893 May 29"The Light on the Marsh,", TMs, 1 p. (Box-folder 2:7)
  - 1893 January 31"The Marching Morrows,", 2 TMs, 2 pp., original typescript and carbon copy (Box-folder 2:8)
  - 1893 May 31"The Prayer in the Rose Garden,", TMs, 1 p. (Box-folder 2:9)
  - 1893 January 31"Quatrain,", TMs, 1 p. (Box-folder 2:10)
  - 1893 March 7"Resignation Rose,", TMs, 1 p. (Box-folder 2:11)
  - 1893 March 15"River Water,", TMs, 4 pp. (Box-folder 2:12)
  - 1893 February 6"Seven Things,", TMs, 1 p. (Box-folder 2:13)
  - 1893 April 28"The Shadow Boatswain,", TMs, 4 pp. (Box-folder 2:14)
  - 1892 September 28"Song", TMs, 1 p. (Box-folder 2:15)
  - n.d.["Songs of the Sea Children XLVII"], TMs, 1 p. (Box-folder 2:16)
  - 1892 December 3"The War Song of Gamelbar,", TMs, 3 pp. (Box-folder 2:17)
  - 1893 February 26"The Wooing of the Wind,", TMs, 1 p. (Box-folder 2:18)
- Series II: Letters
  - 189[3] March 3 B[liss Carman], 125 Indiana Avenue, to [Agnes Cook Gale?], ALS, 7 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 2:19)
    Rejoices that one of his great favorites, "Berris Yare" is going to make its first public appearance in The Independent, edited by Miss Susan Hays Ward, "the same kind hand that gave [his poem] 'Marjorie Darrow' her entre with good society" [published September 1, 1892] and that he has a new poem "just born this afternoon" called "Arnold, Master of the Scud" weighing ninety-two lines and very sturdy. He hopes "to send him to The Youth's Companion to begin his education." He also mentions that Richard [Hovey?] is still in New York working as the Secretary to the Jury of the Theatre of Arts and Letters.
  - 1913 March 14 Bliss Carman, New Canaan, Connecticut, to Agnes Cook Gale, Chicago, Illinois, ALS, 22 pp. on 6 l., with envelope (Box-folder 2:20)
    Mentions the possible summer plans of his friend, Mrs. [Mary Perry] King, also of New Canaan, so that Gale can make her own plans to come East, attempts to explain Unitrinianism, saying "I have been a student of philosophy all my life; not a scholar, of course, but an eager learner. I had to have some faith to live by, some scheme of things which would keep the universe from looking absurd. Unitrinianism has served me well for twenty years." Carman goes on to describe some of the basic tenets and beliefs of Unitrinianism, especially the ideas of Mrs. King's system. He also credits the difficulty of most educators to see the value of harmonizing the whole being to the fact that most of them are men, "And men are much less in need of harmonizing than women. In the first place they are not so delicately constructed, and not so easily distraught and injured by life. Women are often unhinged by sorrow, or unhappiness, or misfortune, that would have no such radical and lasting effect on men at all."
  - 1913 April 2[Bliss Carman], New Canaan, Connecticut, to Agnes Cook Gale. [Dekalb, Illinois?], ALS, 8 pp. on 2 l., on blue stationery, apparently incomplete with large sections marked out in pencil (Box-folder 2:21)
    Shares the feeling of delight expressed by "the Star of Unitrinianism" [Mrs. Mary Perry King] when she receives one of Gale's letters, gives her permission to reprint his poem "Marigolds" and remarks that he has now written eight pages to her without a word of philosophy,
  - [ca. 1913] Bliss Carman to Agnes Cook Gale, ALS, 15 pp. on 4 l., incomplete? (Box-folder 2:22)
    Discusses the fallacies of the Christian Science movement, particularly in the case of the student Miss Flood who wished to study Unitrinianism under [Mrs. Mary Perry King?] but became discouraged,
  - 1914 April 28 Bliss Carman, New Canaan, Connecticut, to Agnes Cook Gale, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 2:23)
    Wonders at the enthusiasm and energy of women, especially Mrs. King and Mrs. [Mesher?], his landlady while he lived in Cambridge and attended Harvard, who had come to visit them in New Canaan, now nearly eighty years old but still "a walking wonder of alert interest and unflagging spirit."
  - 1914 Memorial DayBliss Carman, New Canaan, Connecticut, to Agnes Cook Gale, ALS, 12 pp. on 3 l. (Box-folder 2:24)
    Discusses his difficulties in writing his poem, "Phi Beta Kappa Poem" blaming them on "a cantankerous Muse," mentions "the Star’s [Mary Perry King?]" involvement in a Ballet Dance Festival, remarks upon their wonderful spring, "passing through all the stages from Bluebirds to Bobolinks, from Bloodroot to White Iris," and his upcoming work in the city from the middle of June until August "while the real Editor’s sporting in Europe."
  - 1914 December 21 Bliss Carman, New Canaan, Connecticut, to Agnes Cook Gale, 4 pp. on 1 l.; on stationery of The Bobbs-Merrill Company Publishers, Indianapolis (Box-folder 2:25)
    Wishes her a happy and healthy Christmas, informs her that he must go directly to New York to discuss his four articles with his magazine people instead of coming by Chicago as he had planned, and asks her to have her brother keep him posted as he still hopes to arrange for the dances in [Chicago?] in January.
  - [1916 May] Bliss Carman, New Canaan, Connecticut, to Agnes Cook Gale, 6 pp. on 2 l. incomplete? (Box-folder 2:26)
    Sends her one of the first copies of April Airs, "You must take it as something new and fresh as the spring. It's a pretty volume. There is nothing great in it. But the lines, if they are not as exuberant as of old, are at least not mournful." He continues "The lines 'In Early May' were written on Richard's [Hovey] birthday three years ago, out in the orchard, and I remember I was thinking at the time how much you would love the blossomy time."
  - 1917 January 30 Bliss Carman, New Canaan, Connecticut, to Agnes Cook Gale, ALS, 12 pp. on 3 l. (Box-folder 2:27)
    Apologizes for not promptly signing and returning her copies of The Vagabondia, explains that he has "been up to my ears in a sea of literary remains! Going over mss. and letters and pamphlets and a few [books?], a thousand years old, and trying to put order in the mess," plans to sell letters from departed celebrities to autograph hunters, unless they are too personal, has had a visit from Odell Shepard, a poet and assistant professor of Harvard, who was commissioned to do a biographical study of Carman's literary work, reports that Gladys Baldwin is still renown for her good works at the Church of St. Mary the Virgin, and shares his misgivings about the Pedagogue in Washington [Woodrow Wilson?], "But he is a calamity! The most fickle figure in American history, and the greatest one-man power for evil ever [?] in the nation. No one has yet imagined the disintegrating influence on this generation of his moral cowardice and callous egotism."
  - 1922 February 23 Bliss Carman, New Canaan, Connecticut, to Agnes Cook Gale, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l., incomplete? (Box-folder 2:28)
    Has a reading coming up at her own university on March 7, thanks her for her offer of hospitality during his stay, has also had an offer to speak to the Elizabeth Kirkland Foundation from Mrs. V.K. Spicer [Anne Higginson Spicer of Kenilworth], and mentions a student who wants to write about Richard [Hovey] whose papers may be at Dartmouth.
  - 1926 November 16 Bliss Carman, New Canaan, Connecticut, to Agnes Cook Gale, ALS, 8 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 2:29)
    Writes concerning his return from the Catskills in mid-September, the health of Mary Perry King and her success in finding a music publisher for her rhythms, who will publish a small preliminary prose brochure any day, her happiness with her young companion and nurse, his plans to go to Northern Ontario, Manitoba, and Saskatchewan after the first of the year doing extension work and reading his own work for the universities of various cities, which was a fine success last winter at places like McGill, Toronto, Queens, Winnipeg, Saskatoon, Vancouver, etc., his plans to continue on to the University of California, San Francisco, and the University of Arizona at Tucson, and suggests she read Vachel Lindsay in The Saturday Evening Post for this week.
- Series III: Photographs and Miscellaneous
  - 1922 Black and white photograph post card of Bliss Carman, inscribed on the back "B. with love from Uncle B. / Lake Placid 1922" (Box-folder 2:30)
  - 1893-1894, n.d. Miscellaneous items (Box-folder 2:31)
    including three printed copies of his poems, "Bloodroot," "For a Memorial to John Keats," and "Quaker Ladies"; a typed list of book titles by or concerning Carman; Electrostatic copy of a poem sent to Bliss Carman by Agnes S. Cook, April 15, 1894, "Success is in the Silences, Tho’ fame be in the song"; and an electrostatic copy of an incomplete undated letter from Bliss Carman describing the Muse as a suffragette
  - 1929 Obituaries of Bliss Carman (Box-folder 2:32)